<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Love's pedigree, or, A discourse shewing the grace of love in a believer to be of a divine original delivered in a sermon preached at a lecture in Boston, Febr. 29 1699/1700 / by S. Willard ...</title>
            <author>Willard, Samuel, 1640-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66104</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2283</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39758</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18483172</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18483172</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107845</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66104)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107845)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1644:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Love's pedigree, or, A discourse shewing the grace of love in a believer to be of a divine original delivered in a sermon preached at a lecture in Boston, Febr. 29 1699/1700 / by S. Willard ...</title>
                  <author>Willard, Samuel, 1640-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. Green and J. Allen, sold by Benjamin Eliot ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston in N.E. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John IV, 19 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>God --  Worship and love --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Congregational churches --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, American.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107845:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107845:1"/>
            <p>Love's Pedigree. OR A Diſcourſe ſhewing the Grace of LOVE in a Believer to be of <hi>A Divine Original</hi> Delivered in a SERMON Preached at the Lecture in <hi>Boston, Febr.</hi> 29. 1699./1700</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By <hi>S. Willard,</hi> Teacher of a Church there.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>Jam. 1. 17.</bibl>
            <q>Every good gift, &amp; every perfect gift, is from above, and cometh down from the Father of lights.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>BOSTON,</hi> in <hi>N. E.</hi> Printed by <hi>B. Green,</hi> and <hi>J. Allen.</hi> Sold by <hi>Benjamin Eliot,</hi> at his Shop under the Weſt End of the Town Houſe. 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:107845:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:107845:2"/>
            <head>Love's Pedigree</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 John IV. 19.</bibl>
               <q>We Love him; becauſe he firſt Loved us.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE knowledge of our good and ſafe Eſtate, deriving from an intereſt in the Everlaſting Love of God, is a thing which every one who hath right thoughts of the Eternity he is going to, will be very ſollicitous about. There is, beſides the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of the Spirit of God to this in us, which is neceſſary for our confirmation in the belief of it, the <hi>witneſs</hi> of our own ſpirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, for our ordinary <hi>Aſſurance</hi> about it, which muſt be given to thoſe things in us which are evidential of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Theſe <hi>Evidences</hi> are built upon the diſcovery of ſuch fruits or effects of the love of God wrought in us, as a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e proper and diſtinguiſhing, and theſe are mainly the Graces of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance;</hi> and theſe are
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107845:3"/> put into us by the operation of the Spirit of God, in our <hi>Effectual Vocation;</hi> and becauſe there may be ſomething like unto theſe found in Hypocrites, which may cheat them into falſe and preſumptuous hopes of their good eſtate; there is a yet farther trial to be made of them, to prove that this <hi>Faith</hi> is <hi>unfeigned,</hi> and that this <hi>Repentance</hi> is <hi>unto life,</hi> which muſt be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from thoſe diſtinguiſhing fruits of them, which are not to be found in the other. Theſe <hi>fruits</hi> are all of them in the Word of God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to that common head of <hi>love,</hi> by which <hi>Faith</hi> is ſaid to <hi>Operate, Gal.</hi> 5. 6. Which <hi>Love</hi> is diſtributed according to the next or immediate objects of it, into the <hi>loving of God,</hi> and of our <hi>brother;</hi> and becauſe theſe two are inſeparable, they are therefore made uſe of mutually to evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence each the other; inaſmuch as, if we truly love our brother, it derives from our love to God as the principle, in which it is rooted; and if we love God indeed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it will unfailingly pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the other love in us. So that the grand Caſe into which our <hi>Self Examination</hi> muſt ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately reſolve it ſelf, is, <hi>Whether God loveth us with that love which he bears to his Choſen;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if we are but ſure of this, the inference is infallible, <hi>viz</hi> that we ſhall certainly at laſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at Eternal Life; how happy then muſt we needs be? and the enquiry on which this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion muſt determine, is, <hi>Whether we do cordially
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107845:3"/> and ſincerely love God?</hi> for though our happy ſtate was ſecured for us in the former, it being appointed and ſettled in that love of his, yet we cannot come at the knowledge of it but by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er.</p>
            <p>The words of our <hi>Text</hi> give us a reaſon of the ſafety of this way of concluding, and ſhew us why and wherein it amounts to a <hi>Demonſtration,</hi> in as much as it leads us from the <hi>Effect</hi> to the <hi>ſupream cauſe</hi> from whence it muſt derive. It is needleſs to enquire after the coherence of our <hi>Text</hi> with the <hi>Context,</hi> the words themſelves being an entire propoſition, and having abundant mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of profitable inſtruction in them: and the deſign of them is, not only to aſſert the cloſe connexion that there is between our loving of God, and his loving us; but alſo to point us to the reaſon of this Connexion, and ſhew us the cloſeneſs of it, and the ſafety of our inſerring his love to us from ours to him; and if it be enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to what kind of reaſoning it is to be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? I anſwer, it muſt needs be to the <hi>Efficient Cauſe.</hi> It doth not only intimate that there is a <hi>Concomitancy,</hi> but alſo a <hi>Cauſality:</hi> for, though the word [<hi>becauſe</hi>] doth not always refer us to the cauſe of the thing but may refer to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther head of arguments, and is accordingly to be judged of by the nature of that which it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to; yet it muſt do ſo in this place, inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as we are here given to underſtand the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107845:4"/> priority of Gods love to us, as that from which we come to love him, which can be inferred from no other but the <hi>Efficient.</hi> The word is an <hi>Adjective,</hi> and not an <hi>Adverb;</hi> and that alſo puts force into the argument; he was the <hi>first</hi> in this love, and thence it was that our love followed after. Hence,</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="doctrine">
               <body>
                  <head>DOCTRINE.</head>
                  <p>Our Loving of God is the genuine effect of his firſt Loving of us. If we love him in time, it it becauſe he firſt loved us from Eternity.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>I ſhall not inſiſt on this <hi>Doctrine</hi> at large, but reſtrain the following Diſcourſe to the reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the following <hi>Caſe, viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>In what reſpect Gods love to us is lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to, and influential of our loving of him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That we may take up the right meaning of the Caſe, in order to the better reſolution of it: There are theſe two remarks to be made.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>That by Gods love to us, we are to understand his Eternal purpoſe of good will, by which he appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted us to Salvation by Chriſt. Love</hi> is improperly attributed to God, in whom there are no <hi>Paſſions</hi> or <hi>Affections,</hi> properly ſo called, inaſmuch as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107845:4"/> they argue imperfection, and compoſition in the ſubject of them, which is incompa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ible with the moſt abſolute firſt Being. But becauſe theſe are in men the Inſtruments of the <hi>Will,</hi> by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry whereof it performs its <hi>Imperate Actions,</hi> or they are the various poſtures of it with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to its <hi>Object,</hi> according to the reſentment that it hath of it; hereupon when we ſee ſuch things done in Gods Works of Efficiency, as are wont to be managed by ſuch an <hi>Affection;</hi> we, after our manner of conception, aſcribe it to that <hi>Affection;</hi> becauſe we cannot otherwiſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it. Now <hi>love is an Affection in us, which beareth good will to the Object of it and expreſſeth it ſelf in acts of kindneſs to it.</hi> As therefore it is an Humane Affection, it is rooted in the heart or will, and is on all opportunities diſcovering it ſelf in the carriage; and from this conception of it, when God manifeſteth his benignity to the Creature, we conceive him, in his ſo doing, to act as a cauſe by Counſel, and ſo aſcribe it to his <hi>Benevolence,</hi> and call it his <hi>love.</hi> And fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m this conſideration, there is a divers love that is aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him, according to the different effects of his good will, diſcerned in the fruits of his <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficence</hi> to the Subject of it. There is a <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon love</hi> attributed to him, wherein the good and the bad do promiſcuouſly partake; and it appears in that <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of his which he confers upon them, wherein he gives them large taſts of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107845:5"/> his bounty; and to this love we are pointed in, Pſal. 145. 9. <hi>The Lord is good to all, and his tender mercies are over all his works.</hi> And <hi>Acts 14. 17. He left not himſelf without witneſs in that he did good, and gave us rain from heaven, and fruitful ſeaſons, filling our hearts with food and gladneſs.</hi> And there is an <hi>Eſpecial</hi> love of his that we are told of, which he bears only to ſome, and in compariſon with which others are ſaid to be hated, according to Rom. 9. 13. <hi>Jacob have I loved, and Eſau have I hated;</hi> and it appears in thoſe peculiar favours which he hath laid in for, and beſtows upon them; of which we have ſuch obſervations, <hi>Joh. 3. 16. God ſo loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Joh. 4 9. In this was the love of God manifeſted towards us, becauſe God ſent his only begotten Son into the world, that we might live through him;</hi> and this is the love that we are now conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of, and is intended in our <hi>Text:</hi> which, if we run up to the top of it, is nothing elſe but <hi>that good will of his, by which he purpoſed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow all ſaving good upon us.</hi> There is a <hi>natural</hi> love which we aſcribe to God, by which he loveth himſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lf eternally, being his own laſt end: and with this love every Sacred <hi>Perſon</hi> in the undivided <hi>Trinity</hi> love each other; and there is a <hi>voluntary</hi> love which we conceive in him, which muſt needs flow from his good pleaſure; for we are told, Rom. 9. 18. <hi>He hath mercy on
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107845:5"/> whom he will have mercy.</hi> And ſuch muſt be all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e love which he bears to the Creature, ſince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being, and all that he doth to it or for it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rive from his holy pleaſure, <hi>Who doth all things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ording to the Counſel of his will, Eph.</hi> 1. 11. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was this love that procured our Salvation, <hi>Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 20. Who loved me, and gave himſelf for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>That by our loving of God we muſt understand, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at Cordial reſpect which we have for him, where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we have choſen him for our portion, and are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ely devoted to his fear. Love in us, is an Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction leading us in purſuit after Union to the object <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it, in order to our having intimate Communion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith it:</hi> for love is a <hi>Cloſing</hi> Affection, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rrieth us forth after that which we love. That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich attracts our love to it, is the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich we apprehend to be in the object of it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich renders it a thing lovely; the diſcovery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which goodneſs made to the <hi>Underſtanding,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oves on the <hi>Judgment,</hi> and by that on the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eart,</hi> and draws it out after it. Now the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſion of this love is in <hi>a ſuitable reſpect</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſhew to the object of it, and is accordingly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iverſifyed, as there is a different reference or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion that we bear to it: the love therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Parents to their Children, and of Children <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> their Parents doth not ſhew it ſelf after the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me manner. There are therefore theſe two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings wherein our real love to God appears,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107845:6"/> 
               <hi>Viz.</hi> In our renouncing of all other things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him, chuſing him alone for our portion, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> accordingly depending upon him for all; wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we can ſay as the Church, Lam. 3. 24. <hi>The L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is my portion ſaith my Soul, therefore I will hop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him:</hi> And as the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal. 62. 5. My S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ait thou only upon God, for my expectation is fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him</hi> And in our ſubmitting our ſelves w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> greateſt willingneſs and delight to his Servic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt therefore directs to this as the Evide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our love. <hi>Joh 14 15. If ye love me keep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Commandments.</hi> Love is therefore uſed in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Scriptures to expreſs all that <hi>Obedience</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we pay to God, in ſtudying and practiſing u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verſal conformity to his revealed will. Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rooted in our hearts by the delight we have his precepts; when we can ſay with him, <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 7. 22 I delight in the Law of God after the inw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man.</hi> And it is exerted in our life, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> devote our whole man to New Obedienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>When we love the Lord our God with all our he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and all our ſoul, and all our mind, Matth.</hi> 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>It n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>llows that we proceed to the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion of the Caſe; and we may take it up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the following Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>This love of ours with which we love God, not barely a</hi> Natural Affection, <hi>or a</hi> Moral Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciple <hi>in it, but a</hi> Grace of the Spirit. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tural
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107845:6"/> affection indeed is the Subject of it, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich it is rooted, but we muſt diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>een the affection it ſelf, and the love which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rooted in it. <hi>Love hath Good for its Object;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſuch as the good is, ſo is the love denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ated. We love the things that are ſuited to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur inclinations: and hence there is in Unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enerate m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, a <hi>Carnal Love</hi> which inclines them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the gratification of their carnal Luſts, and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e objects which are ſuited thereto attract <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eir love There is a <hi>Natural Love</hi> in men to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch perſons or things as are agreeable to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atures: and there is a love to the things that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Morally Good and Honest,</hi> which ſome Un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onverted men have in them, and it proceeds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om a principle of Morality, which either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ains in them notwithſtanding the fall, or hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een acquired by them: but none of theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ounts to the love which we are now in the Conſideration of: There is then a <hi>Divine Love,</hi> which carries men out to God, and to Heavenly things, and fixeth them there: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is flows from a ſpecial gracious principle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſed into the man by the Spirit of God, and can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>laim its Original from no other; it is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore called one of the fruits of the Spirit, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the firſt named, <hi>Gal. 5 22. The fruit of the Spirit is love, &amp;c.</hi> This love of God indeed was <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onnatural</hi> to man in his ſtate of integrity, being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne of thoſe Graces of Sanctification which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107845:7"/> were concreated in him, and belonged to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Image of God</hi> which was at firſt put upon hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and adorned him. This love was active a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vigorous in man before ſuch time as he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed himſelf by Sin; and <hi>none of the Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> were grievous to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>The Apoſtaſy robbed man of that holy love God which was at firſt planted in him.</hi> This it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when it ſtript him of the <hi>Image of God,</hi> in wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this and all the other Graces of Sanctificati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were contained. When man put off the Ima<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from him, all that was Spiritual, or <hi>Theologic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> good in him went with it: So that every U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> regenerate man, if he will ſay the Truth, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> confeſs of himſelf entirely, as <hi>Paul</hi> doth of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelf in reſpect to his worſer part, <hi>Rom. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> In me, that is in my fleſh, there dwells no good thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Man, who at firſt loved God as his laſt end a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> chief good, now ceaſeth to do ſo, and there is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one ſpark of that primitive love left in him. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is ſaid of every natural man, <hi>that the love of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Father is not in him, 1 Joh.</hi> 2. 15. The Affecti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of love abides in the man, it being eſſential his Humanity, and inſeparable from it; but hath ſhifted objects, and exchanged God for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Creature; Unconverted men are ſaid to <hi>Lovers of pleaſures, more than lovers of God, 2 Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 3. 4. And hereupon that is one title put up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ungodly men, <hi>Rom. 1. 30. Haters of God.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:107845:7"/> that their firſt love, in reſpect of the object on which it was placed, is turned into hatred.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>This love muſt be again recovered by the man, in order to his being made to enjoy God, and to be happy in him.</hi> It is certain that mans true hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs conſiſts in his enjoying of God, who is the only adequate object of felicity; no other can make a ſuitable and ſufficient portion for the reaſonable Creature: to be far from God, is to be miſerable indeed, <hi>Pſal. 73. 27. For lo, all that are far from thee, ſhall periſh: In his favour there is life; his loving kindneſs is better than life it ſelf.</hi> Now God is a portion for none but thoſe that love him: it is by love that we come to have Communion with him, which is our bleſſedneſs, <hi>Prov. 8. 17. I love them that love me.</hi> Hatred keeps the Sinner at a diſtance from God, and there is a fearful Curſe out againſt all ſuch, <hi>Pſal. 21. 8. &amp;c. Thine hand ſhall find out all thine Enemies, thy right hand ſhall find out thoſe that hate thee; thou ſhalt make them as a fiery Oven, &amp;c.</hi> Whereas there is a great Bleſſing in ſtore for ſuch as love him, <hi>Pſal. 5. 11, 12. Let them that love thy name, be joyful in thee; for thou Lord, wilt bleſs the righteous, with favour wilt thou compaſs him as a ſhield.</hi> It therefore infinitely concerns us all to ſee that the love of God dwells in us; and this is it which the Apoſtle prays for in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107845:8"/> their behalf, 2 Theſ. 3. 5. <hi>The Lord direct your hearts into the Love of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. <hi>It utterly exceeds the power of man to recover this Principle, and the activity of it.</hi> Of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural mans inability to exert any truly Gracious action, the Scripture abundantly informs us, Joſh. 24 19. <hi>Ye cannot ſerve God.</hi> Rom. 8. 7, 8. <hi>The Carnal mind is Enmity againſt God; for it is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſubject to the Law of God, neither indeed can be. So then they that are in the Fleſh, cannot pleaſe God.</hi> 2 Cor. 3. 5. <hi>We are not ſufficient of our ſelves to think any thing, as of our ſelves.</hi> Now this defect ariſeth from the loſs of the Image of God on his Heart, and his incapacity of getting it again by any Endeavour of his own. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath not a root of Grace in him, therefore he cannot act Graciouſly; for <hi>no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Effect can exceed the Vertue of its Cauſe:</hi> And becauſe there is a contrary Principle in him, which reigns over every Faculty and Power within him, he therefore is not able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it. Indeed he cannot ſo much as deſire to Love God, much leſs is he able to reſtore this Grace to his heart again. The Will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as well as the Deed, muſt be of his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration in us, Phil. 2. 13. <hi>It is God who worketh in you to will and to do, of his own good pleaſure.</hi> The reſtoring of loſt Grace to fallen man, is a work of Omnipotency, and therefore none
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107845:8"/> but he who is Almighty is able to do it in us: it is therefore compared to a Creation, 2 <hi>Cor. 4. 6. God who commanded the light to ſhine out of the darkneſs, hath ſhined in our hearts, &amp;c.</hi> And to a Reſurrection, <hi>Eph. 2. 1. You hath he quickned, who were dead in treſpaſſes and ſins.</hi> Love is a thing that is not to be purchaſed; <hi>all that a man would offer for it will be deſpiſed, Cant.</hi> 87. Which may be interpreted as well of our loving God, as of his loving us.</p>
            <p>5. <hi>This love is a ſaving gift, and therefore muſt have God for its Author.</hi> It is one of thoſe things which we are told <hi>do accompany Salvation, Heb.</hi> 69. and is therefore called <hi>a fruit of the Spirit,</hi> in the fore cited, Gal. 5. 22. This love is an effect of the New birth, whereof God is the Author, 1 <hi>John 4. 7. Love is of God, and every one that loveth is born of God.</hi> And indeed, it being one of the Graces of Sanctification, it muſt needs proceed from Gods Efficiency, for it is he that <hi>Sanctifieth us, 1 Theſ.</hi> 5. 23. And the wonderful change that is made in the man by it, muſt force us to ſay of it, <hi>behold the finger of God.</hi> To ſee one who the other day deſpiſed God, had no deſire after him, had him to depart from him, choſe carnal objects, lying vanities rather than him; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay, hated his counſels, and was full of all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices againſt him; now to love him, to chuſe him, to embrace him, to forſake all for him,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107845:9"/> to ſubmit to him, and delight in his Service is a thing of which no other account can be given but <hi>that God hath created him a new in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> that he hath given him another and a <hi>Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heart,</hi> or otherwiſe it could never have been.</p>
            <p>6 <hi>There was nothing in us that could move Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to produce this ſaving quality in us.</hi> In all volun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tary actions, which are done by a Rational A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gent, we are wont to enquire after the <hi>Impulſiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cauſe</hi> of them, or what it was that moved an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> engaged him ſo to do: and by ſuch meaſure as theſe are we neceſſitated to conceive of God Works of Efficiency: It is a demonſtration o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gods wonderful love to us, that he will put principle of Sanctification into us, and thereb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>reſtores us from death to life,</hi> and whence was that he ſo did; or what was it that induce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him hereunto? Certainly it could not be fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any lovelineſs that he ſaw in us, for there wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> none; we had nothing in us that was deſir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, but every thing was hateful: the <hi>Image God,</hi> which once was our beauty and orn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment was gone; and the <hi>Image of Sin,</hi> whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is our ſhame and vileneſs was contracted, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by virtue of it we were every way abomin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble: when therefore God ſpeaks of doing ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> things for backſlidden <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he would hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them to take that humbling remark upon i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ezek. 36. 22. Thus ſaith the Lord, I do not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:107845:9"/> for your ſakes, Oh houſe of Iſrael but for mine holy names ſake, &amp;c.</hi> Nor was he moved here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by our requeſts and prayers; it was not becauſe we, in ſenſe of our folly and miſery, ſought relief of him, that his bowels earned towards us, for he himſelf ſaith, <hi>Iſa. 65. 1. I am ſought of them that asked not for me, I am found of them that ſought me not;</hi> and though he hath declared, in <hi>Ezek. 36. 37. I will yet for this be enquired of by the houſe of Iſrael, to do it for them.</hi> Yet his <hi>preventing grace</hi> produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th this in us, otherwiſe we ſhould never have thus enquired after him, but abode in our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from him.</p>
            <p>7. <hi>Hence the ſpring or riſe of all this must be from his love or good will to us.</hi> When we have ſearched into all the cauſes of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, in which this gracious principle is wrought in us, we muſt ultimately determine it hither: we are made to partake in this Grace, becauſe God hath appointed us to it; and the reaſon why we were ſo appointed, was becauſe it ſo pleaſed God; <hi>Mat. 11. 25. 26. Thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt revealed them to babes; even ſo Father, for ſo it ſeemed good in thy ſight.</hi> God therefore tells <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that he loved them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he loved them; <hi>Deut. 7. 7, 8. The Lord did not ſet his love upon you, becauſe ye were more
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107845:10"/> in number,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but becauſe the Lord loved you.</hi> In timating that the motive of this love was no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> where to be ſought out of himſelf; and on this account God aſſigns our effectual calling to a love of his own that never had any beginning, <hi>Jer. 31. 3. I have loved thee with an everlasting love, therefore with loving kindneſs have I drawn thee;</hi> and needs muſt it be ſo, for he is the firſt cauſe and laſt end of all things, <hi>Rom. 11. ult. Of him, and through him, and to him are all things</hi> Nor could his Grace be otherwiſe abſolutely free, and ſoveraign, as the Goſpel every where aſſures us that it is.</p>
            <p>8. <hi>All the engagements by which our love is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited to act upon him, are from his firſt loving of us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> As there is the planting of ſaving grace in us, in our Renovation, by which a principle is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed into us, enabling and diſpoſing of us to love him, ſo there are the <hi>attractives</hi> by which this principle is drawn forth into act, which are ſo many motives to ſtir up this love in us; for our love of God is not a brui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſh paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion, but it is acted with the higheſt reaſon; and all the reaſons of it are found in his love to us: he therefore thus draws us in order to our following of him; <hi>Cant. 1. 14. Draw me, we will run after thee,</hi> and the way in which he allures us, is by his love, <hi>Hoſ. 11. 4. I drew thee with the cords of a man, with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107845:10"/> the bands of love.</hi> Now there are principally ſuch things as theſe, the conſideration and belief whereof attract the love of our Souls to God.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>It was this love that appointed us to be the heirs of Salvation.</hi> The Word of God doth fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently expreſs our Salvation under the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of an <hi>Inheritance;</hi> and ſo all the claims that we can make to i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, muſt be in way of <hi>Heir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip:</hi> and we are not born heirs to it by a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural birth, but are introduced into it by a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary <hi>Adoption:</hi> we had in our ſelves no more of right to it than the Devils, nor could we make out a better claim to it than the reſt of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate mankind: we were common heirs with them of the ſame deſtruction, <hi>Eph. 2 3. Being children of wrath by nature even as others.</hi> We therefore come to have a right thereto according to appointment, 1 <hi>Theſ. 5. 9. God hath not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed us to wrath, but to obtain Salvation by Jeſus Christ.</hi> Nor can there be a greater obligation upon us to love God, than the conſideration of this eternal deſign: to think that God had ſuch a thought of good will for us, when he propoſed no ſuch favour for millions as good, and as well deſerving as we; and this is owing to his love, 1 <hi>Joh. 3. 1. Behold what manner of love the Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther hath beſtowed upon us, that we ſhould be called the Sons of God?</hi> And ſure this love muſt be more ancient than ours to him, who but the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:107845:11"/> other day hated him, and were his Enemies.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>This love provided Chriſt to purchaſe Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for us.</hi> Such was our unhappy condition by the Fall, that there could be no ſalvation for us, but by a ſatisfaction made to offended Juſtice, which Attribute muſt not in the leaſt vail its glory in this affair, or ſo much as ſtoop to mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in it. If God will ſave us, he muſt provide a <hi>Jeſus</hi> for us, one that can <hi>ſave us from our ſins.</hi> The Law muſt have a reparation made for the violation of it; our contracted Guilt muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piated; we cannot do this for our ſelves, <hi>thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of rams, and ten thouſand rivers of oyl</hi> will not do it; there muſt a <hi>Surety</hi> interpoſe to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake this, none could do it but the Son of God, he muſt be made <hi>Sin</hi> and a <hi>Curſe</hi> for us, he muſt have <hi>all our Iniquities laid upon him, and by his ſtripes we muſt be healed:</hi> the caſe was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to this exigence, either God muſt deſtroy us everlaſtingly for our ſins, or do the execution upon his own Son in our ſtead; nothing elſe would have done: Certainly then here was love unparallel'd: Chriſt himſelf expreſſeth it as that which exceeds all compariſon, <hi>Joh. 3. 16. God ſo loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son:</hi> And the Apoſtle thought it to be an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which could not be over ſtrained, in the exerciſe of our faith for the obtaining of al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the good that is laid up in the promiſe, <hi>Rom</hi> 8
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:107845:11"/> 32. <hi>He that ſpared not his own Son, but delivered him up for us all, how ſhall he not with him alſo freely give us all things?</hi> and the conſideration of it will be further amplified, by obſerving that this was done for us before we had any love for him: not only was it agreed upon in the eternal compact, that Chriſt ſhould in fulneſs of time come, and work out ſalvation for us, but the thing it ſelf was accompliſhed on ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> account during our being his enemies, <hi>Rom. 5. 8, 10. God commends his love towards us, in that while we were yet ſinners, Chriſt died for us. When we were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies we were reconciled to God, by the death of his Son.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. <hi>This love hath revealed Chriſt to us as an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſuitable for us to truſt in for ſalvation.</hi> As it exceeded the reach of any created underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to find out the way of ſalvation by Chriſt: the thing it ſelf being a myſtery of Infinite wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; ſo the <hi>Revelation</hi> or declaration of him to ſinful men is of God alone. It is his <hi>Goſpel</hi> in which Chriſt is publiſhed; there it is that we are acquainted with his Perſon and Offices, his undertaking and accompliſhment, his Incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſubjection to the Law, and making ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to it for us; how acceptable his Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was to his father, how ſufficient it was for us, to procure peace and life for us; there it is that we are acquainted how, and aſſured that <hi>he
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107845:12"/> is able to ſave all thoſe to the uttermoſt that come unto God by him, Heb.</hi> 7. 25. How many nations are there in the world that hear nothing of him, and thereupon they <hi>periſh</hi> unavoidably for <hi>lack of viſion?</hi> Certainly this good news, is a token of Gods good will, it is he who ſends it unto us, and treats with us in it; They that bring theſe glad tidings are his <hi>Ambaſſadors, 2 Cor. 5. 20. We are Ambaſſadors for Chriſt, as if God did beſeech you by us.</hi> It is a treaty of peace and reconciliation which is opened hereby to us, but for which we muſt have remained utter ſtrangers unto peace for ever.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>This love hath pointed out to us the way of Salvation by Christ.</hi> As God hath laid it in Chriſt for us, ſo he hath in the Goſpel diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the way of it to us. There is a <hi>way</hi> in which Sinful men muſt come to partake in the precious fruits of Chriſt Redemption, and there are <hi>terms</hi> on which theſe are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to us; now God hath opened theſe terms, and laid out all the Articles of the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant in his Goſpel. This is not a favour which all partake in: it is ſaid of the Gentiles, who are without the Goſpel, in <hi>Rom. 3. 17. The way of peace have they not known.</hi> And we are told in, 2 <hi>Tim. 1. 10. That God hath brought life and immortality to light through the Goſpel.</hi> There are the propoſals in the New-Covenant
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:107845:12"/> which muſt be complied withal, by thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat hope to be Saved by Chriſt; they that never hear of them, can never comply with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem, <hi>Rom. 10. 14. How ſhall they believe in him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f whom they have not heard.</hi> And it is Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ove to his choſen that moved him to open <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his Covenant and propoſe the terms of it to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem, in order to their being brought into it.</p>
            <p>5. <hi>This love hath not only provided the means, but alſo renders them effectual to our Salvation.</hi> God brings about the Salvation of his Elect in the way of means, as beſt accommodated to his treating of them as reaſonable Creatures; he hath therefore appointed them in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; and they are the <hi>gifts</hi> of our glorified Saviour, <hi>Eph 4. 10. &amp;c.</hi> It is therefore a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar favour for men to enjoy them; there is that remark, <hi>Pſal. 147. 19, 20. He ſhewed his word unto Jacob, his ſtatutes and his judgments unto Iſrael; he hath not dealt ſo with any nation, &amp;c.</hi> And it muſt be ſo, for the want of them is a note of perdition, 2 <hi>Cor 4. 3. If our Goſpel be hid, it is hid to them that are loſt.</hi> But yet many have them, and they prove occaſions of their greater ruine, becauſe they abuſe them: Herein therefore is Gods love, antecedently to ours eminently celebrated, in that he gives a bleſſing to the means, and ſo making them powerful to advance the end of them, <hi>Rom.</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:107845:13"/> 1. 16. <hi>The Goſpel is the power of God to Salvation in them that believe;</hi> and why only in ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do believe? why becauſe the Spirit of God comes in with them to ſuch, and leaves ſaving impreſſions by them. Now all theſe are the incentives of our love, and do certainly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from his loving us firſt.</p>
            <div n="1" type="application">
               <head>USE. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>We may hence infer the Doctrine of perſonal E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection.</hi> Great attempts have been and are uſed in the Chriſtian world to undermine this truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but all are in vain: If there were no more Scripture evidence for the confirmation and eſtabliſhment of this <hi>Article</hi> of our faith, but only the words of our <hi>Text,</hi> it is ſufficient to enervate all the cavils and objections that are brought againſt it. If Gods firſt loving us be not only a <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but a <hi>Cauſe</hi> too of our loving him; and conſequently if any of us have the love of God produced in him, it is an evidence of that antecedent love which he bare to us; it ſo becomes a diſtinguiſhing note between them whom he loved and others; and for that reaſon it muſt needs be an infallible evidence of Gods having ſuch a love for us before, which muſt needs be from Eternity, becauſe his will and purpoſe is like himſelf <hi>Immutable.</hi> And this can amount to nothing leſs than a <hi>Perſonal
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:107845:13"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lection:</hi> for, if God be the author of this Grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> us, and he produceth it by his Spirit becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e loved us, than we were perſonally appointed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ereto from Eternity. So the Apoſtle layes it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>own, <hi>Eph. 1. 3, 4. Bleſſed be the God and Father <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who hath bleſſed us with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll Spiritual bleſſings in heavenly places in Chriſt: according as he hath choſen us in him, before the foundation of the world, that we ſhould be holy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="application">
               <head>USE. II.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>This tells us that Gods Electing love could not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e founded on the previſion of any thing in the Creature.</hi> We are here acquainted with the <hi>Abſolute Sovereignty</hi> of God in this affair. If Gods love be the firſt cauſe of all Grace and Good to us, it muſt needs then be it ſelf <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent,</hi> for that is an inſeparable property of a Supream Cauſe. If Gods love produceth all that is good in the Creature, it is then im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that the goodneſs of the Creature ſhould produce that love to it. To limit Gods ſpecial love which he bears unto any, unto ſomething foreſeen in the Subject, is to make ſomething in us that did precede that, and that did not derive from it as the Efficient of it; which is to invert the order of Cauſes, and put the ſecond being in the place of the firſt. God could not foreſee any thing lovely in us, but upon his own purpoſe to confer it upon us,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:107845:14"/> on which the futurity of it depended; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> therefore this foreſight could not cauſe his lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but muſt needs flow from it. He beſtowed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gift on us becauſe he loved us, <hi>Rev. 1. 5. Un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> him that loved us, and waſhed us fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> our ſins, his blood.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="application">
               <head>USE. III.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hence we learn what little reaſon they have t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> think that God loved them, who are void of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> love of God.</hi> It is true, Gods love to thoſe whom he hath Choſen in Chriſt, runs under groun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for a great while; and there are thoſe whom h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath an endeared reſpect for, who are at preſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in arms of rebellion againſt him, who have n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> regard for him, who <hi>ſay unto him, depart from us</hi> ſuch indeed are all Gods Elect before Converſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on, <hi>Eph<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. 2, 3. Wherein in times past ye walke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> according to the courſe of this world, &amp;c and wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Children of wrath, even as others, Tit. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſelves alſo were ſometimes fooliſh, and di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>obedient &amp;c.</hi> And though there are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſeen ways in which this love of his is before hand working towar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them, yet all this while <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey have no groun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of evidence to prove their intereſt in his ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cial favour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It is certain, if any are the Sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jects of this love it will ſooner or later brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orth in their <hi>Calling,</hi> and will kindle in them a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>incere love to him; <hi>Jer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 31 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I have loved th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:107845:14"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith an everlaſting love, therefore in loving Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſs have I drawn thee.</hi> And this is the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſcovery by which they know that he loved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem, 2 Theſ. 2. 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>God hath from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing choſen you to Salvation, through the Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cation of the Spirit.</hi> And therefore the order <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f <hi>Aſſurance</hi> is to come at the knowledge of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur <hi>Election</hi> by our <hi>Vocation, 2 Pet.</hi> 1. 10. In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain then do they pretend to be the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oved of God, who do not love and ſerve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im cordially.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="application">
               <head>USE. IV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hence it follows, that they who truely love God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>annot but acknowledge and adore his Electing love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o them.</hi> What is the reaſon why the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing World, is ſo full of prejudices againſt the Doctrine of <hi>Gods free Sovereign Election,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat there are ſo few that can reliſh, or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iently endure the Preaching of it? Doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t muſt be becauſe they were never experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally acquainted with it. That man who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath had <hi>the love of God ſhed abroad in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and hath known what it is to be <hi>Saved by Grace,</hi> will put the greateſt Emphaſis upon this Article of it; and his love will be the more ardently enflamed by it, to think that herein God hath manifeſted what precious and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:107845:15"/> endearing thoughts he had for him in the da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Eternity; how diſtinguiſhing that love w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> when he had neither being nor deſervin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <closer>My Prayer then for all ſuch prejudiced perſons ſhall be, that God will give unto them the experience of this love in themſelves, and that will ſilence all their up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſings of heart, and fill them with adoration.</closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:107845:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
